Daniela Gioseffi Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Daniela Gioseffi papers
1960-2018
YCAL MSS 1096
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.83
(14 boxes)
The Daniela Gioseffi Papers, which span from 1960 to 2018, contain correspondence, writings, printed material, electronic media, and other papers related to the life and work of Daniela Gioseffi. Correspondence makes up the bulk of the collection, documenting Gioseffi's personal and business relationships with poets, authors, critics, and cultural luminaries. Audiovisual materials and electronic media in the collection document interviews, readings, and other events with which Gioseffi was involved.
Gioseffi, Daniela
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 9, 13 (audiocassettes): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 10-11 (digital media): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Daniela Gioseffi, 2016-2018.
Arrangement
Organized into five groupings: I. Correspondence, 1960-2015. II. Personal Papers and Memorabilia, 1970-2013. III. Textbooks, 1981-1989. IV. Interviews and Recordings, 1974-2016. V. December 2018 Acquisition, circa 1960-2018.
Biographical / Historical
Daniela Gioseffi is an Italian-American poet, novelist, and critic, born in New Jersey in 1941. She studied at Montclair University and Catholic University of America before going on to produce sixteen books of poetry and prose. Gioseffi teaches in New York City and has won numerous awards including the American Book Award in 1990 for her book "Women on War: International Writings from Antiquity to the Present".
Scope and Contents
The Daniela Gioseffi Papers, which span from 1960 to 2018, contain correspondence, writings, printed material, electronic media, and other papers related to the life and work of Daniela Gioseffi. Correspondence makes up the bulk of the collection, documenting Gioseffi's personal and business relationships with poets, authors, critics, and cultural luminaries. Audiovisual materials and electronic media in the collection document interviews, readings, and other events with which Gioseffi was involved.
American poetry -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 21st century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 21st century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 21st century -- Archives; Women authors; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 21st century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 21st century; Gioseffi, Daniela
- Correspondence, circa 1960-2015; Series I; 2.08; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Material within this series maintains the original organization found at time of acquisition.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains correspondence (incoming and outgoing), along with poetry, other writings, and ephemera that were included with the correspondence. The material documents personal and business relationships related to Daniela Gioseffi.
  - Correspondence--A, circa 1978-1997 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--A-B, 1983-2012 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--A-B, 1983-2012 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--C, circa 1986-2010 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--D-E, circa 1985-2003 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--F-G, circa 1974-2010 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--H-J, circa 1972-1986 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--K-L, circa 1960s-2015 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence--M, circa 1960s-2015 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence--N-P, circa 1973-2015 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence--Q-R, circa 1970-1976 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence--S, circa 1975-1994 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence--T-V, 1990-2016 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence--W, circa 1978-2015 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence--X-Z, 1982-1998 (Box 2)
  - Bly, Robert, circa 1970s-2002 (Box 3)
  - Ciardi, John, circa 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Cuomo, Mario; Ferraro, Geraldine, 1984-1986 (Box 3)
  - Gioia, Dana; Knott, Bill; Robbins, Tom, circa 1972-1980 (Box 3)
  - Gardner, Isabella, circa 1970-1982 (Box 3)
  - Ignatow, Rose Graubart, 1981-1987 (Box 3)
  - Ignatow, Rose Graubart, 1981-1987 (Box 4)
  - Ignatow, Rose Graubart, 1981-1987 (Box 4)
  - Interviews, circa 2001-2011 (Box 4)
    This file contains interviews conducted by and with Daniela Gioseffi. Subjects/participants include Meena Alexander, Bob Holman, Galway Kinnell, Robert Pinsky, Grace Paley, D. Nurkse, Ishmael Reed, William Pitt Root, and Sapphire.
  - Kinnell, Galway, circa 1984-2013 (Box 4)
  - Poulin, Al; BOA Editions, Ltd., circa 1970-1989 (Box 4)
  - Poulin, Al; BOA Editions, Ltd., circa 1970-1989 (Box 4)
  - Poulin, Al; BOA Editions, Ltd., circa 1970-1989 (Box 4)
  - Poulin, Al; BOA Editions, Ltd, circa 1970-1989 (Box 5)
  - Poulin, Al; Logan, John, circa 1970-1977 (Box 5)
  - Poulin, Al; Logan, John, circa 1970-1977 (Box 5)
  - Poulin, Al; Logan, John, circa 1970-1977 (Box 5)
  - Snodgrass, W. D., circa 1978-1984 (Box 5)
- Personal papers and memorabilia, 1970-2013; Series II
  These materials include articles, posters from events, information about travel and readings, awards, and papers related to Daniela Gioseffi's life and work.
  - Personal papers and memorabilia, circa 1970-2013 (Box 6)
  - Personal papers and memorabilia, circa 1970-2013 (Box 6)
  - Personal papers and memorabilia, circa 1970-2013 (Box 6)
  - Personal papers and memorabilia, circa 1970-2013 (Box 6)
  - Personal papers and memorabilia, circa 1970-2013 (Box 6)
  - Personal papers and memorabilia, circa 1970-2013 (Box 6)
  - Personal papers and memorabilia, circa 1970-2013 (Box 6)
  - Personal papers and memorabilia, circa 1970-2013 (Box 6)
  - Emily Dickinson article--research and documentation, 2010-2013 (Box 6)
  - Women on War: International Writings, circa 2003-2006 (Box 7)
    Includes reviews, flyers, advertisements, publicity, letters, and articles related to Gioseffi's book, "Women on War: International Writings".
  - Women on War: International Writings, circa 2003-2006 (Box 7)
  - Women on War: International Writings, circa 2003-2006 (Box 7)
- Textbooks, 1981-1989; Series III; 1.08; (1 box)
  Material within this series are arranged chronologically by date of publication.
  These are textbooks were used for teaching purposes; several include work by Daniela Gioseffi.
  - "Living Literature: American Voices" textbook, 1981 (Box 8)
  - "Living Literature: American Voices" teacher's manual and answer key, 1981 (Box 8)
  - "Structure and Meaning: An Introduction to Literature" textbooks, 1983 (Box 8)
  - "Literature: Options for Reading and Writing" textbook, 1989 (Box 8)
  - "The Story of English" textbook, 1986 (Box 8)
  - "The Story of English" activity and answer books, 1988 (Box 8)
- Interviews and recordings, 1974-2016, undated; Series IV; 1.08; (3 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Box 9 (audiocassette): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Boxes 10-11 (digital media): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Material within this series are arranged chronologically by date of creation.
  This series contains audiovisual materials that document events, poetry readings, and interviews related to Daniela Gioseffi's life and creative work.
  - Black Box 4 audiocassette, 1974; 1 (Box 9)
  - Interviews related to "Women on War", circa 1988; 1 (Box 10)
  - Brian Leher "On the Line" with Daniela Gioseffi, 1993-1994; 1 (Box 10)
  - Robert Bly and Daniela Gioseffi poetry reading in Lowell, MA, 1995; 1 (Box 10)
  - Daniela Gioseffi Sings Jazz, 1999; 1 (Box 10)
  - Daniela Gioseffi interviews Bob Holman, 2001; 1 (Box 10)
  - Daniela Gioseffi interviews Galway Kinnell, 2001; 2 (Box 10)
  - Daniela Gioseffi poetry reading with Lee Briccetti at Bryant Park, 2002; 1 (Box 10)
  - Conversation with Daniela Gioseffi, 2003; 1 (Box 10)
  - Conversation with Daniela Gioseffi, 2003; 1 (Box 10)
  - Original poems and songs, 2003; 1 (Box 10)
  - Original poems and songs, 2003; 1 (Box 10)
  - American Book Awards--Women on War, 2005; 1 (Box 10)
  - Memories of James Wright, 2010; 1 (Box 10)
  - "Wild Nights" book launch at Poets House, 2010; 1 (Box 10)
  - Poetry reading at Cornelia Street Cafe, 2011; 1 (Box 10)
  - Daniela Gioseffi at Poets House, 2011; 1 (Box 11)
  - Ernesto Cardenal and Daniela Gioseffi at Poets House, 2011; 1 (Box 11)
  - Poetry reading at Poets House, 2011; 1 (Box 11)
  - Eco-poetry event at Poets House, 2013; 1 (Box 11)
  - "Pioneering Italian Culture" book launch at CUNY, 2013; 1 (Box 11)
  - "Pioneering Italian Cultures" book launch at CUNY--Tributes, 2013; 1 (Box 11)
  - "Italics" interview with Daniela Gioseffi on CUNY TV, 2014; 1 (Box 11)
  - Author and Activist: The Daniela Gioseffi Story, 2016; 1 (Box 11)
  - Book cover images, undated; 1 (Box 11)
  - Digital photographs of Daniela Gioseffi, plus other poets and authors, undated; 1 (Box 11)
    Photographs on this disc were taken circa 1970-2007.
  - John Logan memorial, undated; 1 (Box 11)
  - John Logan memorial, undated; 1 (Box 11)
  - John Logan reading "Only the Dreamer Can Change the Dream", undated; 1 (Box 11)
  - "The Poet and the Poem" from the Library of Congress, undated; 1 (Box 11)
  - Poetry reading, undated; 1 (Box 11)